A Guide to the Richard Watson Gilder Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7135-a
Richard Watson Gilder Collection
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7135-a
50 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Informaiton
Deposit 22 Jul 1964
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem, " On the Life-Mask of Abraham Lincoln ", 1907 Nov 16; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, " The Christ-Child ", n. d.; AMs, 1 p.
    [Initialed]
  - Poem, " A Letter to John Burroughs ", n. d.; AMsS, 11 p.
    [Includes an initialed note by Gilder stating that the poem was later called "
    The Building of the Chimney
    "; begins, "My chimney is builded.. ."]
  - Poem, " On a Portrait of Servetus ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, " The Singing River ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Includes note on top of page, "This is the original for Mrs. [Aldrich]."]
  - Poem, " Two Optimists ", n. d.; AMs, 2 p.
  - Essay, " American Sentiment Concerning Russia and Japan ", AMs, 18 p.
    [Missing pages 2-6.]
  - Editorial, " The Christmas Century ", n. d.; AMs, 5 p.
  - Editorial, " A Law-Regarding Race ", n. d.; AMs, 2 p.
  - Essay, " The Only Literary Success Worth Having ", n. d.; AMs, 4 p.
  - Essay, " A Test of Character ", n. d.; AMs, 3 p.
  - Editorial, " Ten Thousand Manuscripts ", AMs, 7 p.
  - Poem, " A Soul Lost and Found ", TMsS, 2 p.
    [Includes autograph corrections.]
- Letters
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Mr. Seymour, 1871 Apr 27; ALS, 1 p.
    [Wonders if he wants any of Scribner's Japan pictures for his series Travel and Adventure.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, Bordertown, New Jersey, to Dr. [ Robert Bridges], 1876 Oct 13; ALS, 4 p.
    [Talks about a novel by Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen; says it seems more foreign than
    Gunnar
    although it depicts life in an American Western Norwegian settlement; adds that the novel needs work, but that he considers it worth publishing in the magazine.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Mrs. Foot, 1877 May 23; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he is sorry about her ill health; mentions a short story she has in the works; says he has been to see Frances Hodgson Burnett and that she is writing a new serial for him; praises Burnett's play, "
    Esmeralda
    . "]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1880 Jun 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Praises his piece "
    The Lost Hellos
    "; says that the "Dr." agrees that the piece is in "excellent form --heathenish but heavenly"; discusses business.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Epes Sargent, New York, 1880 Sep 22; ALS, 4 p.
    [Asks for help in selecting pieces for the "encyclopedia"; suggests several titles, including Charles deKay's
    Hespherus and Other Poems
    (1880).]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Dr. William Hayes Ward, New York, 1885 Oct 24; ALS, 2 p.
    [Press copy in secretarial handwriting and signature; discusses a piece that may appear in
    Century Magazine
    . ]
  - Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy, Castle Hill, Virginia, to Richard Watson Gilder, New York, 1886 Apr 4; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses her piece "
    Goranne de Savare
    " which he has sent to her to correct.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Dr. William Hayes Ward, [ New York], 1888 Apr 24; TLS, 2 p.
    [Discusses poem, "
    The Innovation
    " by Ward; Gilder agrees with Lewis Frank Tooker, of the
    Century
    staff; criticizes content and style of the poem and suggests changes for both; says poem reminds him of Swinburne and Whitman.]
  - Charles F. Chichester, New York, to Richard Watson Gilder, 1888 Sep 5; ALS, 2 p.
    [Speaks of an enclosed letter that will interest him; says he has information that Scribner's will send an expedition to Russia; wonders if their own friend in Moscow has definite information on it, but has mixed them up; reports on progress repairing the Century Building on 17th Street; says the mantel in Gilder's office with Dr. Howard's relief was destroyed and wonders if he has taken measures to replace the original carving with a replica; comments in postscript on a book by Peter Cooper on Jefferson which the Century Co. is not going to publish; says he is afraid the family will not make money from the book because of small sales.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Bishop John Fletcher Hurst, Washington, D. C., 1890 Jan 30; TLS, 1 p.
    [Says he would like to see Hurst's paper on the "Salzburg Exiles"; says he is convinced the bishop will make a good thing of it.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Dr. William Hayes Ward, New York, 1890 Dec 5; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends him some material he requested.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Herbert Dickinson Ward, 1893 Nov 29; TLS, 1 p.
    [Says he is pleased that Ward likes the illustrations by [A.] Castaigne; states that the story will appear in the February number.]
  - Sir Charles George Douglas Roberts to Richard Watson Gilder, 1896 Aug [1]; ALS, 1 p.
    [Welcomes him and his wife to Canada; hopes Mrs. Gilder's health is improved; quotes a line of "native Canadian verse."]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Dr. William Hayes Ward, [ New York], 1896 Nov 29; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he is not sure that Ward will like his frankness; asks for a prompt return of the manuscript.]
  - Samuel Reynolds Hole, [ England], to Richard Watson Gilder, [ England], 1898 Jul 22; ALS, 2 p.
    [Admires the
    North American Review
    appreciates the invitation for literary contribution; says his time is, however, limited because he is writing a book [
    Our Gardens
    ]; wishes him a successful visit to England. ]
  - Bronson [Crocker] Howard to Richard Watson Gilder, New York, 1899 May 25; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends him part of a proposed article; says he is very unsure of the piece as he is used to writing dramatic dialogue only; asks for perfect frankness from him; talks about illustrations for the article.]
  - Laurence Alma-Tadema, London, England, to Richard Watson Gilder, New York, 1899 Oct 13; ALS, 1 p.
    [Offers a short novel for possible publication in 3 parts to
  - George Madden Martin(Mrs. Atwood R. Martin), Louisville, Kentucky, to Richard Watson Gilder, New York, 1900 Sep 19; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for the verdict on her manuscript; confesses that she had doubts about it herself after sending it off; apologizes for sending it.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Florence Nightingale Levy, New York, 1900 Oct 4; TLS, 1 p.
    [Notifies her that the business proposition relating to the American Art Annual has been rejected; says it would be too expensive for the club; with autograph sentence.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, Four Brooks Farm, Lee, Massachusetts, to Thomas Bailey Aldrich, 1901 Aug 6; ALS, 4 p.
    [Looks forward to the Aldrich family's visit to Four Brooks Farm; gives directions to farm and description of it; says they will discuss proper attire for Aldrich to appear in at Harvard and Yale[to receive honorary degrees ?] there and then; tells him that Professor Wein's tailor is the one to engage; speaks at length about the academic gowns for both occasions.]
  - Cyrus Townsend Brady, Cape May, New Jersey, to Editor of Century Magazine [ Richard Watson Gilder], New York, 1901 Aug 23; ALS, 4 p.
    [Returns galleys to "
    Under the Ban of the Redbeard
    "; says the story should be called "Barbarossa," a more captivating name for a book as well as a play, which he intends to do; defends his usage of the words "King" and "Kaiser," citing Caesar and the Roman Empire; explains his attitude toward the use of capital and lower case letters for titles; wishes to put under his name in galley 1, "author of
    The [Guiberon] Touch
    and
    Colonial Fights and Fighters
    , " the titles of his last books to be published in the fall; asks for a set of proofs of the illustrations.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to [ Elizabeth Stuart Phelps] Ward, [ Massachusetts], 1902 Feb 25; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says he is locked up at home with a "blooming" cold; speaks about a letter he has sent her; gives her permission to use the letter as she pleases; says he will sign what she sends him; pleads with her not to overexert herself for the cause.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, East Gloucester, Massachusetts, to Herbert Dickinson Ward, 1902 Aug 29; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says Ward has been mentioned as one author who may have written "
    The Confessions of a Wife
    "; asks him to assist in the concealment of authorship by returning to affirm or deny the rumor; says he heard of Ward's possible authorship from the "traveler."]
  - Bertha Reunkle, [ New York], to Richard Watson Gilder, New York, 1902 Nov 11; ALS, 3 p.
    [Sends him the manuscript of a story she has not quite finished; reminds him that he asked to see it some time ago.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Mr. Chambers, 1903 Jan 14; ALS, 1 p.
    [Refuses to publish his piece in
    says the story regards suicide and is controversial.]
  - Clarence Clough Buel, New York, to Richard Watson Gilder, New York, 1903 Sep 28; ALS, 1 p. w/AN
    [Discusses the December issue of
    informs him that there is room for [John] Burroughs, [Henry Cabot] Lodge, and [George Henry] Sargent as well as ["
    The Bigoudines
    "], an illustrated article; asks for his wishes and ideas; mentions the pleasant news of Gilder's progress. Includes initialed AN by Gilder and autograph note, initialed by Gilder, remarking on the contents and looks of the December issue of
    ]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, [ New York], to Herbert Dickinson Ward, 1903 Dec 30; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he is at home on the mend; tells him it might be necessary to see Mr. [ Robert Underwood] Johnson who is running things at
    expresses New Year's wishes.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, Lee, Massachusetts, to Robert Underwood Johnson, New York, 1904 Oct 13; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses poetic work by Gilder which Johnson has looked at and made suggestions about; compliments him for devoting so much attention to details of composition, etc., even though he is busy as an editor.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Elizabeth Stuart Phelps Ward, [ Boston], 1904 Nov 3; ALS, 4 p.
    [Discusses a book she wrote expressing her anti-vivisection views; discusses her following of homeopathic medicine and vegetarianism; speaks of his own revulsion to hunting, fishing, even eating mutton; leans toward a vegetarian diet; speaks accusingly of landlords near his farm in Massachusetts, Trinity Church, the director of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and of Abraham Lincoln; says that "Gentle Lincoln" assisted in the vivisection and maiming of myriads, without anesthesia, and destroyed millions of human lives to free the slaves.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, [ New York], to Harry Thurston Peck, 1904 Dec 29; ALS, 2 p.
    [Tries to meet with him to speak about a print in the current chapter of his history.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, Lee, Massachusetts, to Thomas Bailey Aldrich, 1905 Sep 4; ALS, 4 p.
    [Talks about a woman writer whose "charming" novel
    Four Ways to Paradise
    was published by the Century Co., but who does not write much any more these days; hopes the rainy weather will stop for Aldrich's visit; says they had a reading the night before of favorite pieces by Aldrich, of which a verse was appreciated by their old friend, the Marquis di Rosalis, though he is not familiar with it; gives directions for coming by trolley from Pittsfield to Lee, should he miss the connection.]
  - William Webster Ellsworth, New York, to Richard Watson Gilder, Tyringham, Massachusetts, 1906 Jul 30; TLS, 2 p.
    [Discusses a trip to California, a meeting with Mary Austin in San Francisco, the possibility of serializing one of her books [
    Isidro
    ]; mentions her other books and poetry, published by Houghton, Mifflin, and Co.; mentions writing of Bret Hart and George Washington Cable; says he dissuaded Austin from moving to the east coast; discusses other Century Co. business; includes autograph note.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Elizabeth Stuart Phelps Ward, [ Massachusetts], 1907 Dec 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [Talks about a fine copy of the praying hands by [Albrecht] Durer and a book about Durer that he owns; mentions Christmas; says he is very happy with a houseful of children; says he has had a setback in his health and is still at home because of it; says she is the kindest person he knows.]
  - Richard Watson Gilder, New York, to Florence Nightingale Levy, New York, 1909 Apr 22; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses an old mantelpiece in his house, 13 East 8th Street, which he considers poor architecture, not a good Colonial example; says she is welcome to look at; includes autograph sentence.]
  - Fanny Heaslip Lea, New Orleans, to Richard Watson Gilder, New York, 1910 Jan 14; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses her short story, "
    Little Anna and the Gentleman Adventurer
    " which she sent to
    says it has not been acknowledged; written after Gilder's death in November 1909.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Proof of poem, " Hymn ", 1881 Jul; Proof, 1 p.
    [Includes autograph notes, initialed.]
- Picture
  - Portrait of Richard Watson Gilder, with caption, clipped from a magazine, n. d.; Engraving